<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-05T07:54:49-05:00</updated><id>https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Cloudera Solutions Engineer</title><subtitle>Solutions Engineer @Cloudera</subtitle><author><name>Steven Matison</name></author><entry><title type="html">Cloudera AI Inference Service GA Onpremise</title><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-AI-Inference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloudera AI Inference Service GA Onpremise" /><published>2026-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2026-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera%20AI%20Inference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-AI-Inference/"><![CDATA[<p>We’re excited to announce the <strong>general availability (GA)</strong> of the Cloudera AI Inference service for on-premises deployments. This milestone marks a significant expansion of our private AI vision, allowing enterprises to deploy, scale, and govern the latest generative AI (GenAI) models directly within their own data centers.</p>

<p>Powered by <strong>NVIDIA NIM</strong>, the Cloudera AI Inference service provides the control and performance that enterprises need to accelerate innovation without compromising data security.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="empowering-true-private-ai">Empowering True Private AI</h2>
<p>Cloudera AI Inference for on-premises is engineered for organizations that demand absolute control over their intellectual property and data sovereignty.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Complete Data Privacy:</strong> Ensure that sensitive data, prompts, and model responses never leave your secure corporate network, meeting strict regulatory requirements.</li>
  <li><strong>Air-Gapped Readiness:</strong> Full support for highly secure, air-gapped environments, providing the tools and documentation necessary to import and manage models without external connectivity.</li>
  <li><strong>Storage Flexibility:</strong> Full support to any S3-compatible object storage.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="predictable-tco-for-production-ai">Predictable TCO for Production AI</h2>
<p>As enterprises move from experimentation to steady-state production, the on-premises service offers a significantly lower total cost of ownership (TCO) compared to token-based cloud APIs*.</p>

<p>The AI Inference on-premises service lowers long-term TCO by providing ownership of GPU infrastructure, which pays off fast when inference happens 24/7.</p>

<h2 id="feature-highlights-for-production-grade-ai">Feature Highlights for Production-Grade AI</h2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Optimized Performance:</strong> Prebuilt and optimized engines, including <strong>TensorRT-LLM</strong> and <strong>vLLM</strong>, ensure low-latency, high-throughput inferencing.</li>
  <li><strong>Seamless Integration:</strong> Integrate with existing MLOps workflows and CI/CD pipelines using OpenAI-compatible APIs for large language models (LLMs) and Open Inference Protocol APIs for traditional models.</li>
  <li><strong>Comprehensive Monitoring:</strong> Track performance metrics such as latency, throughput, and resource utilization in real-time to ensure operational continuity.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="get-started-today">Get Started Today</h2>
<p>The Cloudera AI Inference service enables enterprises to achieve high-performance, private AI with a significantly lower TCO than cloud-based APIs. By keeping workloads on-premises, customers ensure absolute data sovereignty and predictable costs for production-scale GenAI.</p>

<p>To get started, visit the <strong>Model Hub</strong> to select from a catalog of optimized models ready for deployment within your secure environment.</p>

<p>As always, check out the entire <a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/machine-learning/1.5.5/index.html">DOCS</a> for Cloudera Data Lineage.</p>

<p>If you would like a deeper dive, hands on experience, demos, or are interested in speaking with me further about Cloudera Data Lineage,  please reach out to schedule a discussion.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Matison</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="cloudera" /><category term="ai" /><category term="inference" /><category term="onpremise" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re excited to announce the general availability (GA) of the Cloudera AI Inference service for on-premises deployments. This milestone marks a significant expansion of our private AI vision, allowing enterprises to deploy, scale, and govern the latest generative AI (GenAI) models directly within their own data centers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing Cloudera Data Lineage</title><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Data-Lineage/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing Cloudera Data Lineage" /><published>2026-02-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2026-02-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Data-Lineage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Data-Lineage/"><![CDATA[<p>In a significant move to conquer “metadata chaos,” <strong>Cloudera</strong> officially acquired <strong>Octopai</strong> in late 2024. This acquisition marks a pivotal moment in Cloudera’s evolution from a big data pioneer to a comprehensive Hybrid Data and AI leader.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="a-brief-history-from-hadoop-to-hybrid-ai">A Brief History: From Hadoop to Hybrid AI</h2>

<p>Cloudera’s journey began in 2008 as a visionary in the Apache Hadoop ecosystem, eventually merging with its primary rival, Hortonworks, in 2019. Since then, the company has pivoted aggressively toward the <strong>Cloudera Data Platform (CDP)</strong>, a hybrid solution that manages data across on-premises and multi-cloud environments.</p>

<p>Octopai, founded in 2016, carved out a niche as the gold standard for automated data discovery and lineage. By the time of the merger, Octopai was already famous for its ability to map complex data environments in seconds—something that traditionally took manual weeks or months. By bringing Octopai into the fold, Cloudera has essentially added the “GPS” to its massive data warehouse and lakehouse offerings, allowing users to see exactly where their data comes from and where it is going.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="cloudera-data-lineage-powering-the-era-of-convergence">Cloudera Data Lineage: Powering the “Era of Convergence”</h2>

<p>Now fully integrated as <strong>Cloudera Data Lineage</strong>, the platform has received a massive overhaul to support the modern data estate. Cloudera has introduced over <strong>60 native connectors</strong> designed to bridge the gap between traditional big data systems and real-time streaming architectures.</p>

<h3 id="deep-integration-with-nifi-and-kafka">Deep Integration with NiFi and Kafka</h3>
<p>A standout update is the deep integration with <strong>Apache NiFi (Cloudera DataFlow)</strong> and <strong>Apache Kafka</strong>. The new NiFi connectors allow for <strong>“cross-system lineage,”</strong> meaning as data is ingested from the edge and transformed through various processors, the lineage is captured automatically. This prevents the “black box” effect often seen in data-in-motion.</p>

<p>Similarly, the <strong>Kafka connectors</strong> enable organizations to track ephemeral streaming data, ensuring that real-time insights are just as governed and auditable as static data in HDFS or S3.</p>

<h3 id="ai-driven-governance">AI-Driven Governance</h3>
<p>Beyond just connectivity, Cloudera has added the <strong>Octomize AI agent</strong>, which uses generative AI to help data teams optimize SQL queries and automatically document data flows. These features transform Cloudera Data Lineage from a simple map into an active intelligence layer, essential for meeting the strict requirements of GDPR, HIPAA, and the governance needs of enterprise-scale AI.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Key Takeaway:</strong> The fusion of Octopai’s metadata discovery engine with Cloudera’s big data backbone provides Cloudera Data Lineage; a unified view of data health, from the first spark of ingestion to the final AI model.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As always, check out the entire <a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/octopai/latest/index.html">DOCS</a> for Cloudera Data Lineage.</p>

<p>If you would like a deeper dive, hands on experience, demos, or are interested in speaking with me further about Cloudera Data Lineage,  please reach out to schedule a discussion.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Matison</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="cloudera" /><category term="octopai" /><category term="data" /><category term="lineage" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In a significant move to conquer “metadata chaos,” Cloudera officially acquired Octopai in late 2024. This acquisition marks a pivotal moment in Cloudera’s evolution from a big data pioneer to a comprehensive Hybrid Data and AI leader.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Get Up To Speed With Cloudera AI 2026</title><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-AI/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Get Up To Speed With Cloudera AI 2026" /><published>2026-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2026-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-AI</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-AI/"><![CDATA[<p>Happy New Year!!!   It’s been quite some time since I had a moment to blog, and I figured the start of the new year was a good time to post about how much Cloudera has been doing in the AI space.   Now, what kind of human would I be if i wasnt using AI to talk about AI?   First, let’s ask my second favorite AI, Gemini to summarize Cloudera from Machine Learning to AI.  Then lastly, I will provide you with a collection of materials so you can study up on Cloudera and AI for 2026.</p>

<p><b>0 to 100 mph Lets go!!</b></p>

<p>My prompt:</p>

<p><b><i>
  Write a short summary of how cloudera went from machine learning to ai in the last 3 to 5 years
</i></b></p>

<p>Gemini Reply, with human edits:</p>

<h1 id="clouderas-evolution-from-big-data-to-enterprise-ai-20212026">Cloudera’s Evolution: From Big Data to Enterprise AI (2021–2026)</h1>

<p>In the last 3 to 5 years, Cloudera has undergone a major strategic transformation, shifting from a focus on <strong>Big Data and Machine Learning (ML)</strong> to becoming a comprehensive <strong>Enterprise AI platform</strong>.</p>

<p>This transition was driven by the market’s move from predictive models to <strong>Generative AI (GenAI)</strong> and the need for businesses to run AI on their own data without compromising security.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="the-strategic-pivot-20212023">The Strategic Pivot (2021–2023)</h3>
<p>Cloudera began moving away from its legacy as a Hadoop-based “Big Data” company toward the <strong>Cloudera Data Platform (CDP)</strong>, a hybrid data cloud. During this phase:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>From ML to AI:</strong> The company rebranded “Cloudera Machine Learning” to <strong>Cloudera AI</strong>. This signaled a shift toward embedding intelligence into business processes rather than just building isolated models.</li>
  <li><strong>The Data Lakehouse:</strong> They popularized the “Open Data Lakehouse” (built on <strong>Apache Iceberg</strong>), which provided the structured, governed foundation necessary for large-scale AI.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-generative-ai--agentic-era-20242025">The Generative AI &amp; Agentic Era (2024–2025)</h3>
<p>With the explosion of GenAI, Cloudera shifted its product roadmap to support Large Language Models (LLMs) and autonomous agents.</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Strategic Acquisitions:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Verta (May 2024):</strong> Acquired for its AI operational platform to strengthen model management and “ModelOps.”</li>
      <li><strong>Octopai (Nov 2024):</strong> Added automated data lineage to ensure AI models use trustworthy, traceable data.</li>
      <li><strong>Taikun (Aug 2025):</strong> Integrated Kubernetes management to allow AI workloads to run seamlessly across any cloud or on-prem environment.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>AI-Specific Tools:</strong> They launched <strong>Cloudera AI Studios</strong> and <strong>AMPs</strong> (Accelerators for Machine Learning Projects), providing templates for RAG (Retrieval-Augmented Generation) and AI agents.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>

<p>As promised, please find the following resources and references that I have collected to help you get up to speed with Cloudera and AI.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/products/machine-learning/ai-studios/product-tour.html">Agent Studio Product Tour</a></p>

<p><a href="https://app.getreprise.com/launch/W6G3ON6/">Agent Studio</a></p>

<p><a href="https://app.getreprise.com/launch/9yKdqN6/">Hybrid Product Tour - Evolve25</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/products/machine-learning.html">Cloudera AI</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/why-cloudera/enterprise-ai.html">Enterprise AI</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/products/machine-learning/ai-workbench.html">Cloudera AI Workbench</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/products/machine-learning/ai-studios.html">Cloudera AI Studios</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/campaign/the-future-of-enterprise-ai-agents.html?internal_keyplay=AI&amp;internal_campaign=Thought-Leadership-Reports---AlwaysOn-FY26-Q1-GLOBAL-CT-Report-The-Future-of-Enterprise-AI-Agents&amp;cid=701Ui00000SH4IQIA1&amp;internal_link=p11">The Future of AI Agents</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/campaign/the-evolution-of-ai-the-state-of-enterprise-ai-and-data-architecture.html?internal_keyplay=AI&amp;internal_campaign=Thought-Leadership-Reports---AlwaysOn-FY26-GLOBAL-CT-Report-State-of-Enterprise-AI-Survey&amp;cid=701Ui00000cKCojIAG&amp;internal_link=p11">The State of Enterprise AI and Data Architecture</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/content/dam/www/marketing/resources/ebooks/unleashing-the-power-of-generative-ai-in-your-business.pdf.landing.html">Unleashing the Power of Generative AI in Your Business</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/blog/business/context-is-the-hard-part-practical-lessons-in-building-agentic-ai-system.html">Context Is the Hard Part: Practical Lessons in Building Agentic AI Systems</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/blog/business/deliver-repeatable-measurable-and-enterprise-ready-ai-for-life-sciences.html">Deliver Repeatable, Measurable, and Enterprise-Ready AI for Life Sciences</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/blog/business/2026-predictions-the-architecture-governance-and-ai-trends-every-enterprise-must-prepare-for.html">2026 Predictions: The Architecture, Governance, and AI Trends Every Enterprise Must Prepare For</a></p>

<p>As always, check out the entire <a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/machine-learning/cloud/product/topics/ml-product-overview.html">DOCS</a> for Cloudera Ai.</p>

<p>If you would like a deeper dive, hands on experience, demos, or are interested in speaking with me further about Cloudera and AI,  please reach out to schedule a discussion.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Matison</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="cloudera" /><category term="ai" /><category term="agent" /><category term="ai studio" /><category term="cml" /><category term="amp" /><category term="ai workbench" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Happy New Year!!! It’s been quite some time since I had a moment to blog, and I figured the start of the new year was a good time to post about how much Cloudera has been doing in the AI space. Now, what kind of human would I be if i wasnt using AI to talk about AI? First, let’s ask my second favorite AI, Gemini to summarize Cloudera from Machine Learning to AI. Then lastly, I will provide you with a collection of materials so you can study up on Cloudera and AI for 2026.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cloudera Streams Messaging - Kubernetes Operator 1.4</title><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Streams-Messaging-Kubernetes-Operator-1.4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloudera Streams Messaging - Kubernetes Operator 1.4" /><published>2025-07-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera%20Streams%20Messaging%20Kubernetes%20Operator%201.4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Streams-Messaging-Kubernetes-Operator-1.4/"><![CDATA[<p>The Data In Motion team is thrilled to announce the release of Cloudera Streams Messaging - Kubernetes Operator 1.4 and the exciting new Cloudera Surveyor! This release marks a significant step forward in simplifying and enhancing your Apache Kafka management experience on Kubernetes, focusing on intuitive user experience and powerful new capabilities.</p>

<h1 id="release-highlights">Release Highlights</h1>

<h2 id="introducing-cloudera-surveyor-your-new-go-to-for-seamless-kafka-management-on-kubernetes">Introducing Cloudera Surveyor: Your New Go-To for Seamless Kafka Management on Kubernetes</h2>
<p>Cloudera Surveyor is a brand-new, intuitive graphical interface built to streamline the monitoring and management of your Apache Kafka clusters running on Kubernetes. As a core component delivered with Cloudera Streams Messaging - Kubernetes Operator 1.4, Surveyor empowers you with:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Effortless Management: Move beyond the command line with a modern, easy-to-use UI for all your Kafka operations.</li>
  <li>Multi-Cluster Visibility: Manage and monitor multiple Kafka clusters from a single, centralized console.</li>
  <li>Actionable Insights: Get real-time health and performance metrics that help you quickly identify and resolve issues.</li>
  <li>Enhanced Security: Benefit from built-in TLS, robust LDAP authentication, and enforcement of Kafka ACLs.</li>
  <li>Enterprise Scalability: Designed to handle large-scale deployments, Surveyor scales to manage hundreds of Kafka clusters, brokers, and topics.</li>
  <li>Broad Kafka Compatibility: Manage diverse Kafka deployments consistently across on-premises, cloud, or Kubernetes environments.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="cloudera-streams-messaging---kubernetes-operator-14-the-foundation-for-your-kubernetes-native-kafka">Cloudera Streams Messaging - Kubernetes Operator 1.4: The Foundation for Your Kubernetes-Native Kafka</h2>
<p>Cloudera Streams Messaging - Kubernetes Operator 1.4 provides the robust and reliable foundation necessary for deploying and managing Kafka clusters, including the new Cloudera Surveyor. This update brings continued stability and improvements to your containerized Kafka deployments, ensuring a seamless experience for upgrades and operations within your Kubernetes environments.</p>

<h2 id="unified-data-in-motion-portfolio-beyond-kafka">Unified Data In Motion Portfolio: Beyond Kafka</h2>
<p>This launch further strengthens Cloudera’s comprehensive Data In Motion portfolio. While Cloudera Streams Messaging - Kubernetes Operator and Cloudera Surveyor significantly enhance your Kafka experience, our solutions span the entire real-time data lifecycle. Our portfolio also includes powerful offerings for data ingestion and transformation with Apache NiFi, and advanced stream processing and analytics with Apache Flink, providing a complete ecosystem for your event-driven architectures.</p>

<h2 id="who-benefits-from-cloudera-surveyor-and-when">Who Benefits from Cloudera Surveyor and When?</h2>
<p>Cloudera Surveyor is designed to bring clarity, control, and efficiency to anyone managing Apache Kafka on Kubernetes, whether you’re an administrator, a DevOps engineer, or a developer.</p>

<h3 id="for-kafka-administrators--sres-site-reliability-engineers">For Kafka Administrators &amp; SREs (Site Reliability Engineers):</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Daily Operations &amp; Health Monitoring: Easily oversee the health of all your Kafka clusters, brokers, and topics from a single dashboard. Quickly spot anomalies, monitor resource utilization, and ensure the continuous availability of your streaming infrastructure.</li>
  <li>Proactive Troubleshooting: When issues arise, drill down into performance metrics, consumer group lag, and topic details with an intuitive UI. Identify bottlenecks, misconfigurations, or problematic consumers faster, significantly reducing mean time to resolution (MTTR).</li>
  <li>Scaling &amp; Capacity Planning: Gain insights into topic growth, partition distribution, and broker load to inform your scaling decisions and optimize resource allocation across your Kubernetes environment.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="for-devops--platform-engineers">For DevOps &amp; Platform Engineers:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Streamlined Deployments &amp; Upgrades: While Cloudera Streams Messaging - Kubernetes Operator handles the heavy lifting, Surveyor provides immediate visual confirmation of your deployed Kafka clusters, enabling quick validation post-deployment or upgrade.</li>
  <li>Consistent Multi-Cluster Management: For organizations running numerous Kafka clusters (e.g., for different departments, environments, or applications), Surveyor offers a centralized management plane, drastically simplifying oversight and ensuring consistent configurations and security policies.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="for-developers-working-with-kafka">For Developers working with Kafka:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Understanding Topic &amp; Consumer Behavior: Quickly inspect topics, view message counts, and monitor consumer group progress. This is invaluable for debugging applications, verifying data flow, and understanding how new features or changes impact the Kafka ecosystem during development and testing phases.</li>
  <li>Security &amp; Access Management: Easily review and manage Kafka ACLs directly through the UI, ensuring that applications and users have appropriate access to topics and consumer groups, without resorting to complex command-line operations.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>
<p>Ready to explore Cloudera Streams Messaging - Kubernetes Operator 1.4 and Cloudera Surveyor? Find out more here:</p>

<p>New - <a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/csm-operator/1.4/surveyor-overview/topics/csm-op-surveyor-overview.html">Cloudera Surveyor Documentation</a></p>

<p>New - <a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/csm-operator/1.4/release-notes/topics/csm-op-rn.html#concept_ksn_nwn_cbc">Cloudera Streams Messaging - Kubernetes Operator 1.4 Release Notes</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/products/stream-processing.html">Cloudera Streaming Product Page</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/events/webinars/accelerate-streaming-pipeline-deployments-with-new-kubernetes-operators.html">Accelerate Streaming Pipeline Deployments with New Kubernetes Operators</a> (webinar recording)</p>

<p>As always, check out the entire <a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/csm-operator/1.4/index.html">DOCS</a> for the CSM Operator.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Matison</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="csm" /><category term="kafka" /><category term="kubernetes" /><category term="cloudera" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Data In Motion team is thrilled to announce the release of Cloudera Streams Messaging - Kubernetes Operator 1.4 and the exciting new Cloudera Surveyor! This release marks a significant step forward in simplifying and enhancing your Apache Kafka management experience on Kubernetes, focusing on intuitive user experience and powerful new capabilities.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cloudera Streaming Analytics - Kubernetes Operator 1.3</title><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Streaming-Analytics-Kubernetes-Operator-1.3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloudera Streaming Analytics - Kubernetes Operator 1.3" /><published>2025-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera%20Streaming%20Analytics%20-%20Kubernetes%20Operator%201.3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Streaming-Analytics-Kubernetes-Operator-1.3/"><![CDATA[<p>Cloudera’s Data In Motion Team is pleased to announce the release of the Cloudera Streaming Analytics - Kubernetes Operator 1.3, an integral component of Cloudera Streaming - Kubernetes Operators.</p>

<p>This release includes rebases to Apache Flink 1.20 and Apache Flink Kubernetes Operator 1.11.0. Other changes and updates are focused on enhancing security, usability, and making the product more robust.</p>

<h3 id="release-highlights">Release Highlights</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Rebase to Flink 1.20</strong>
  For more information, see the <a href="https://flink.apache.org/news/2024/07/22/flink-1.20-release.html">Flink 1.20 Release Notes</a> and the <a href="https://nightlies.apache.org/flink/flink-docs-release-1.20/">Flink 1.20 Documentation</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Rebase to Flink Kubernetes Operator 1.11.0</strong>
  For more information, see the <a href="https://github.com/apache/flink-kubernetes-operator/releases/tag/v1.11.0">Flink Kubernetes Operator 1.11.0 Release Notes</a> and the <a href="https://nightlies.apache.org/flink/flink-kubernetes-operator-docs-release-1.11/">Flink Kubernetes Operator 1.11.0 Documentation</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Flink OpenTelemetry Metrics Reporter (Technical Preview)</strong>
  The OpenTelemetry metrics reporter is now included, in Tech Preview, in the operator image. It makes it easier and more efficient to aggregate job metrics to a central service like Prometheus or any OpenTelemetry-compatible service, and aggregate metrics using open standards. To learn more about using the OpenTelemetry reporter with Flink, see <a href="https://nightlies.apache.org/flink/flink-docs-release-1.20/docs/deployment/metric_reporters/opentelemetry/">Monitoring Flink with OpenTelemetry</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Flink image with Hadoop, Hive, Iceberg, and Kudu connectors</strong>
  Cloudera now offers alternative images for Cloudera Streaming Analytics - Kubernetes Operator that include popular connectors and their dependencies. This makes it easier to launch jobs right after installation and saves time because there’s no need to create custom images. For more information, refer to the Operator’s <a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/csa/1.3.x/kubernetes-operator/concepts/csa-k8s-operator-images.html">Documentation</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Basic authentication for Flink UI and rest API</strong>
  The Operator now includes the Flink Basic Authentication Handler, enabling users to secure their deployments without the need for external or third-party JARs.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Please see the <a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/csa/1.3.x/kubernetes-operator/release-notes/csa-k8s-operator-rn.html">Release Notes</a> for the complete list of fixes and improvements.</p>

<h3 id="getting-the-new-release">Getting the New Release</h3>

<ul>
  <li>To upgrade to Cloudera Streaming Analytics - Kubernetes Operator 1.3, check out the <a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/csa/1.3.x/kubernetes-operator/installation/csa-k8s-operator-upgrade.html">Upgrade Guide</a>.</li>
  <li>If you are installing this operator for the first time, consult the <a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/csa/1.3.x/kubernetes-operator/installation/csa-k8s-operator-install.html">Installation Guide</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="use-cases">Use Cases</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Event-Driven Applications:</strong> Stateful applications that ingest events from one or more event streams and react to incoming events by triggering computations, state updates, or external actions. Apache Flink excels in handling the concept of time and state for these applications, and can scale to manage very large data volumes (up to several terabytes). It has a rich set of APIs, ranging from low-level controls to high-level functionality, like Flink SQL, enabling developers to choose the most suitable options for the implementation of advanced business logic. One of Apache Flink’s most popular features for event-driven applications is its support for savepoints. A savepoint is a consistent state image that can be used as a starting point for compatible applications. With a savepoint, an application can be updated or adapt its scale, or multiple versions of an application can be started for A/B testing.
  <strong>Examples:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Fraud detection</li>
      <li>Anomaly detection</li>
      <li>Rule-based alerting</li>
      <li>Business process monitoring</li>
      <li>Web application (social network)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Data Analytics Applications:</strong> With a sophisticated stream processing engine, analytics can be performed in real time. Streaming queries or applications ingest real-time event streams and continuously produce and update results as events are consumed. The results are written to an external database or maintained as internal state. A dashboard application can read the latest results from the external database or directly query the internal state of the application. Apache Flink supports streaming as well as batch analytical applications.
  <strong>Examples:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Quality monitoring of telco networks</li>
      <li>Analysis of product updates and experiment evaluation in mobile applications</li>
      <li>Ad-hoc analysis of live data in consumer technology</li>
      <li>Large-scale graph analysis</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Data Pipeline Applications:</strong> Streaming data pipelines serve a similar purpose as Extract-Transform-Load (ETL) jobs. They transform and enrich data and can move it from one storage system to another. However, they operate in a continuous streaming mode instead of being periodically triggered. Hence, they can read records from sources that continuously produce data and move it with low latency to their destination.
  <strong>Examples:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Real-time search index building in e-commerce</li>
      <li>Continuous ETL in e-commerce</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="resources">Resources</h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/products/streaming-analytics.html">New - Cloudera Streaming Analytics Community Page</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/products/streaming-analytics/kubernetes-operator.html">New - Cloudera Streaming Analytics - Kubernetes Operator Product Page</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://blog.cloudera.com/cloudera-streaming-analytics-kubernetes-operator-1-3-release/">New - Cloudera Streaming Analytics - Kubernetes Operator 1.3 Blog Post</a> (to share)</li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/csa/1.3.x/kubernetes-operator/index.html">Updated - Cloudera Streaming Analytics - Kubernetes Operator Documentation</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/webinars/streaming-analytics-overview.html">Cloudera Streaming Analytics Overview (webinar recording)</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Steven Matison</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Cloudera Streaming Analytics" /><category term="flink" /><category term="cloudera" /><category term="kubernetes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cloudera’s Data In Motion Team is pleased to announce the release of the Cloudera Streaming Analytics - Kubernetes Operator 1.3, an integral component of Cloudera Streaming - Kubernetes Operators.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cloudera Flow Management on DataHub 2.2.9 GA for Cloudera 7.3.1.400</title><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Flow-Management-2.2.9-General-Availability/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloudera Flow Management on DataHub 2.2.9 GA for Cloudera 7.3.1.400" /><published>2025-07-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Flow-Management-2.2.9%20General%20Availability</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Flow-Management-2.2.9-General-Availability/"><![CDATA[<p>The Data in Motion Team is pleased to announce the General Availability (GA) release of Cloudera Flow Management 2.2.9 supporting Apache NiFi 2.3.0 and 1.28.1 for Cloudera Data Platform 7.3.1.400.</p>

<p>This release offers a number of new features and improvements as well as upgraded dependencies.</p>

<h3 id="key-features-for-this-release">Key features for this release</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>NiFi 2.3:</strong> Cloudera Flow Management 2.2.9 for DataHub contains an image based on Apache NiFi 2.3.0 and adds several new features not available in previous versions of Apache NiFi.
    <ul>
      <li><strong>New Features and Components in Apache NiFi 2.3:</strong>
        <ul>
          <li>Support for copying and pasting flow definitions between separate NiFi deployments</li>
          <li>Several new processors integrating with Box, allowing users to leverage Box as a cloud storage solution</li>
          <li>GetS3ObjectTags - Retrieves object tags for a file in S3</li>
          <li>PEMEncodedSSLContextProvider - an SSLContext Provider configurable using PEM Private Key and Certificate files, providing a more secure solution for TLS-based connections</li>
          <li>StandardDatabaseDialectService - A controller service to generate SQL statements for the specified database dialect (MySQL, Oracle, e.g.), providing a simpler approach for configuring database-related processors to support various SQL dialects</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><strong>New Components in Cloudera Flow Management 2.2.9 for DataHub (based on Apache NiFi 2.3.0):</strong>
        <ul>
          <li>SawmillTransformRecord and SawmillTransformJSON - Uses the Sawmill transformation DSL to transform incoming FlowFiles, providing an additional and powerful method to transform FlowFile content</li>
          <li>New controller services providing better integration with Cloudera Flow Management Registry</li>
          <li>PhoenixThickConnectionPool and PhoenixThinConnectionPool - Database Connection Pool controller services integrating with Phoenix (SQL on HBase) either using the thin or thick driver (both included), enabling more connections from NiFi, such as to Cloudera Operational Database</li>
          <li>RESTCatalogService (in Technical Preview) - Catalog controller service for integrating with external REST-based Iceberg catalogs such as Apache Polaris</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>New GenAI Python Processors:</strong> Cloudera Flow Management 2.2.9 for DataHub adds four new Python processors to help develop RAG pipelines. PromptClaude, TokenCount, PromptAzureOpenAI, and PromptOpenAI are included in the release. For the associated applications, users can design a full RAG pipeline.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>New Flow Analysis Rules:</strong> Cloudera Flow Management 2.2.9 for DataHub adds two new Flow Analysis Rules: RequireMergeBeforePutIceberg and RestrictFlowFileExpiration. The former ensures FlowFiles will not be too small as to affect the performance of Iceberg; the latter restricts the minimum time for a FlowFile to expire in the system and be removed, which helps prevent data loss if FlowFiles remain idle in a connection past the specified threshold.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Critical Component Support:</strong> CFM 2.2.9 includes the Solr, Spark, and Elasticsearch Beats components that were removed in Apache NiFi 2.0. For users with existing flows that use these, or looking to take advantage of them in new flows, Cloudera’s distribution of NiFi 2.0 will be the only way to gain access to and support for these components.</p>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Updates and Patches:</strong> For additional stability, performance, and security.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="support-matrix-and-upgrade-paths">Support Matrix and Upgrade Paths</h3>

<p>To upgrade, users should:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Upgrade their CFM DataHubs to Cloudera Flow Management 2.2.9 (based on Apache NiFi 1.28.1) first</li>
  <li>Then utilize the Cloudera Flow Management Migration tool to convert existing Cloudera Flow Management flows to run on Cloudera Flow Management 2.2.9 (based on Apache NiFi 2.3.0) instances.</li>
</ol>

<p>Cloudera Flow Management 2.2.9 for DataHub is supported on Cloudera Cloudera Data Platform 7.3.1 Service Pack 2. In-place upgrades from Cloudera Flow Management for DataHub (based on Apache NiFi 1.x) to Cloudera Flow Management for DataHub (based on Apache NiFi 2.x) are not supported; flows must be migrated then transferred to the Cloudera Flow Management 4 instance(s).</p>

<h3 id="use-cases">Use Cases</h3>

<p>Leverage NiFi 2.x capabilities with Cloudera enhancements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Exercise NiFi 2 capabilities in production with Cloudera’s first NiFi 2 based Generally Available release for DataHub.</li>
  <li>Flow administrators can enforce best practices for flow designers to ensure robust, reliable solutions using the Flow Analysis Rules Engine and Cloudera-provided flow analysis rules.</li>
  <li>Create RAG pipelines for GenAI, Data Engineering, and Machine Learning model scoring using new processors and integrations.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<p><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/cdf-datahub/7.3.1/release-notes/topics/cdf-datahub-whats-new.html">Release Notes</a></p>

<p><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/cdf-datahub/7.3.1/release-notes/topics/cdf-datahub-whats-new-flow-management.html">What’s New with Nifi 1</a></p>

<p><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/cdf-datahub/7.3.1/release-notes/topics/cdf-datahub-whats-new-flow-management-nifi2.html">What’s New with  Nifi 2</a></p>

<p><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/cdf-datahub/7.3.1/release-notes/topics/cdf-datahub-whats-new-edge-management.html">What’s New with MiNiFi</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Matison</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="cloudera" /><category term="nifi" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Data in Motion Team is pleased to announce the General Availability (GA) release of Cloudera Flow Management 2.2.9 supporting Apache NiFi 2.3.0 and 1.28.1 for Cloudera Data Platform 7.3.1.400.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cloudera Data Services On Premises 1.5.5 General Availability</title><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Data-Services-1.5.5-GA/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloudera Data Services On Premises 1.5.5 General Availability" /><published>2025-06-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-06-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera%20Data%20Services%201.5.5%20GA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Data-Services-1.5.5-GA/"><![CDATA[<p>Cloudera is thrilled to announce the general availability (GA) of Data Services 1.5.5*. This is a significant milestone tailored to meet the security, reliability, and scalability requirements of many on-premises Data Services customers. Key capabilities of this release are: Cloudera AI Inference tech preview, cert-manager integration for non-wildcard certificates, Cloudera AI Workbench scalability and performance improvements, Cloudera Data Engineering Access Control Lists (ACLs), Cloudera Data Warehouse Hive query history, and a significant reduction in common vulnerabilities and exposures (CVE).</p>

<h1 id="key-features-and-benefits-of-this-release">Key features and benefits of this release</h1>

<ul>
  <li>Cloudera AI Workbench:
    <ul>
      <li>AI Studios [Technical Preview]
        <ul>
          <li>Low-code tools simplify the development, customization, and deployment of generative AI solutions</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Cloudera Copilot [Technical Preview]
        <ul>
          <li>AI-powered coding assistant for seamless integration within JupyterLab ML Runtimes</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Model Hub [Technical Preview]
        <ul>
          <li>Catalog of top-performing LLM and generative AI models</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Spark in Cloudera AI Improvements</li>
      <li>User and Team Sync enabled by default</li>
      <li>Multiple Docker registry account support</li>
      <li>Support for Cloudera Base 7.3.1.300 for Cloudera AI Workbench-only deployments</li>
      <li>Removal of wildcard Certificate requirement through use of Cert Manager</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Cloudera AI Inference (New Data Service):
    <ul>
      <li>Technical Preview of our AI Inference service for on-premises</li>
      <li>Capability to deploy both open-source and NVIDIA NIM-based LLMs on GPUs</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Cloudera Data Engineering:
    <ul>
      <li>Multi-tenant / Multi-team security model (ECS only)
        <ul>
          <li>New User Management Service (UMS)  roles for granular access controls: administrative delegation and access restrictions per VC  (by group &amp; user)</li>
          <li>Application artifact ACLs:  Virtual cluster artifacts including jobs, job runs, resources, sessions, and repositories are now controlled by object level access control lists</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Streamlined onboarding
        <ul>
          <li>Self-service user onboarding:  Users that will execute applications on the cluster, can on-board their Kerberos credentials using a new self-service workflow.  Removes the need for the previous administrative utility scripts</li>
          <li>Removal of wild card certificates: During service and VC creation, the system will automatically set up self-signed certs, which can later be updated with custom certificates by an administrator via UI/API/CLI. Third-party certificate manager Venafi is also supported</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Improved security posture via hardened Images
        <ul>
          <li>Spark runtimes now use Chainguard to reduce CVEs and include upgraded components, like Python 3.10 and 3.11</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Cloudera Data Warehouse:
    <ul>
      <li>Hive and Impala query history
        <ul>
          <li>A scalable solution for storing and analyzing historical Hive query data. It captures detailed information about completed queries, such as runtime, accessed tables, errors, and metadata, and stores it in an efficient Iceberg table format</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Cloudera Data Warehouse provides you with the option to enable logging Impala queries on an existing Virtual Warehouse or while creating a new Impala Virtual Warehouse</li>
      <li>OpenTelemetry support for Hive</li>
      <li>Enhancements for Hue SQL AI Assistant including support for Cloudera AI Inference  connectivity, multi-database querying, and user input validation controls</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Cloudera Data Visualization:
    <ul>
      <li>Version 7.2.9 is now available, bringing improvements for job and user management, dataset versioning, and AI Visual creation</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Data Services Platform:
    <ul>
      <li>Automated certificate management via cert manager integration (ECS only)
        <ul>
          <li>Cert-manager is an open-source tool for Kubernetes that automates the provisioning, management, and renewal of TLS certificates. It gives customers an option to not use wildcard certificates by default and instead use their certificate issuers to provision certificates</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Istio support (ECS only)
        <ul>
          <li>Istio integration in Cloudera’s platform enables Cloudera Data Engineering’s ACL features as well as Cloudera AI Inferencing authorization capabilities.The Control plane uses Istio in ambient mode, while Cloudera AI and Cloudera Data Engineering are currently using Istio in sidecar mode</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Improved ECS upgrade reliability via prechecks
        <ul>
          <li>Host Health Status, EcsHostDnsInspection, Security Software Inspection, Control plane health check, Docker registry health check</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Better quota management and resource utilization for multi-base cluster deployment
        <ul>
          <li>Manage and allocate quotas: setup, at time of the service or workload, sets the logical boundaries (quotas)</li>
          <li>Enforce quotas: applies the logical boundaries, runtime, queues new workloads that do not fit in quota</li>
          <li>Enables multiple Base clusters to interact with a single control plane</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Cloudera support for Apache Iceberg version 1.5.2</li>
      <li>Certifications include 7.1.9 Service Pack 1 Cumulative Hot Fix (CHF) 5, Red Hat Enterprise Linux 9.5, Openshift Container Platform 4.17, Rancher Kubernetes Engine 2 1.30</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>CVEs:
    <ul>
      <li>91% reduction in total CVEs in those images, bringing the count down from 98,000 (in 1.5.4 Cumulative Hot Fix 1) to 8,000</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="support-matrix-and-upgrade-paths">Support Matrix and Upgrade Paths</h1>
<p>To upgrade to the 1.5.5 release, you must ensure Cloudera Manager is upgraded to 7.13.1.300 with a supported base cluster version - 7.1.7 SP3, 7.1.9, 7.1.9 SP1. In case a customer intends to use cert manager for data services, it can only be supported via a fresh installation on 1.5.5 ECS; upgrades are not supported at this time.1.5.5 will be upgradeable from 1.5.3, 1.5.4, 1.5.4 CHF1, 1.5.4 CHF2, 1.5.4 CHF3, 1.5.4 SP1, and 1.5.4 SP2.</p>

<p>For Cloudera AI Workbench-only cluster deployments, the 1.5.5 release is certified to work with Cloudera Base 7.3.1.300 release. 7.3.1 certification for other data services will follow soon.</p>

<h1 id="links">Links</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/cdp-private-cloud-data-services/1.5.5/release-notes/topics/cdppvc-release-notes.html">Release notes</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/cdp-private-cloud-data-services/1.5.5/release-notes/topics/cdppvc-1-5-5-Repository-Locations.html">Download</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://supportmatrix.cloudera.com/">Support Matrix</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.cloudera.com/services-and-support/support-lifecycle-policy.html">Support lifecycle policy</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Steven Matison</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="cloudera" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cloudera is thrilled to announce the general availability (GA) of Data Services 1.5.5*. This is a significant milestone tailored to meet the security, reliability, and scalability requirements of many on-premises Data Services customers. Key capabilities of this release are: Cloudera AI Inference tech preview, cert-manager integration for non-wildcard certificates, Cloudera AI Workbench scalability and performance improvements, Cloudera Data Engineering Access Control Lists (ACLs), Cloudera Data Warehouse Hive query history, and a significant reduction in common vulnerabilities and exposures (CVE).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cloudera Flow Management Migration Tool 3.0.0 for NiFi 1 to NiFi 2 migrations now GA</title><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Nifi-2.0-Migration-Tool-GA/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloudera Flow Management Migration Tool 3.0.0 for NiFi 1 to NiFi 2 migrations now GA" /><published>2025-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera%20Nifi%202.0%20Migration%20Tool%20GA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Nifi-2.0-Migration-Tool-GA/"><![CDATA[<p>The Data in Motion team is pleased to announce the generally available (GA) release of Cloudera Flow Management Migration Tool 3.0.0.  This tool assists Cloudera customers in migrating from Cloudera Flow Management 2.1.7 Service Pack 2 (powered by NiFi 1) to Cloudera Flow Management 4.10.0 (powered by NiFi 2).</p>

<h1 id="key-features-and-benefits-of-this-release">Key features and benefits of this release</h1>

<ul>
  <li>Streamlined NiFi 1 to NiFi 2 migrations: The Cloudera Flow Management Migration Tool dramatically simplifies migrating data flows designed for NiFi 1 to run in NiFi 2, and helps you transition to Cloudera Flow Management 4.x more efficiently.  It facilitates migrations in compliance with the NiFi 1.28-to-2.3 GA ruleset to ensure a smooth and effective migration experience, covering missing, modified, and replaced components. The tool also automates complex and repetitive tasks in updating flow configurations, reducing manual effort.</li>
  <li>Aligned with NiFi 2 features: This command-line tool transforms variables and components to align with NiFi 2 features.</li>
  <li>Improved flexibility: This release allows you to migrate a flow in its “flow.json.gz” form, where no unzipping/rezipping need to take place.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="support-matrix-and-upgrade-paths">Support Matrix and Upgrade Paths</h1>

<p>Cloudera Flow Management Migration Tool 3.0.0 is a standalone product that supports the conversion of flows from Cloudera Flow Management 2.1.7 Service Pack 2 to run on Cloudera Flow Management 4.10.0.0 instances. This release supports on-premises environments.</p>

<h1 id="links">Links</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/cfm/4.10.0/cfm-migration-tool/topics/cfm-mt-release-notes.html">Release notes</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://archive.cloudera.com/p/cfm-migration-tool/">Download</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Steven Matison</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="nifi" /><category term="cloudera" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Data in Motion team is pleased to announce the generally available (GA) release of Cloudera Flow Management Migration Tool 3.0.0. This tool assists Cloudera customers in migrating from Cloudera Flow Management 2.1.7 Service Pack 2 (powered by NiFi 1) to Cloudera Flow Management 4.10.0 (powered by NiFi 2).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cloudera Flow Management - Kubernetes Operator 2.10</title><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Flow-Management-Kubernetes-Operator-2.10/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloudera Flow Management - Kubernetes Operator 2.10" /><published>2025-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera%20Flow%20Management%20Kubernetes%20Operator%202.10</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-Flow-Management-Kubernetes-Operator-2.10/"><![CDATA[<p>The Data In Motion Team is pleased to announce the release of Cloudera Flow Management - Kubernetes Operator version 2.10.</p>

<p>This release introduces NiFi 2 to the Cloudera Flow Management - Kubernetes Operator. In addition, it includes features that help with developer productivity, flow stability, operational overhead, and quality of life.</p>

<h2 id="release-highlights">Release Highlights</h2>
<ul>
  <li>NiFi 2 general availability: NiFi 2 is now an available option when deploying NiFi in a Kubernetes cluster using the Cloudera Flow Management - Kubernetes Operator.</li>
  <li>FIPS mode: Customers can now declare additional security providers, such  as CryptoComply for Java and Bouncy Castle, to ensure FIPS (Federal Information Processing Standard) compliance.</li>
  <li>Out of memory (OOM) recovery: The Operator can now recover proactively from OOM events in NiFi based on user-provided configuration parameters.</li>
  <li>Cluster scheduling: The NiFi custom resource now contains a schedule spec that can define the times during which a NiFi cluster will run.</li>
  <li>Environment variables: In the NiFi spec, users can set custom environment variables on the NiFi container for use in Flows or Python scripts.</li>
  <li>NAR volume providers: NARs can be landed in a networked filesystem or object storage and provided to NiFi by way of a CSI driver, i.e. EFS or S3.</li>
  <li>OIDC authentication: Support for OpenID Connect authentication has been added to the NiFi Registry spec. This enables integration of the NiFi Registry with Keycloak.</li>
  <li>Additional CA bundles reference: Additional CA certificates can now be provided by a Secret or ConfigMap reference instead of in-line in the NiFi spec yaml, greatly reducing file length and improving readability.</li>
  <li>Additional proxy hosts: A NiFi spec field has been added, and multiple hostnames can now be provided to NiFi. This allows configuration of alternate DNS names for the NiFi service beyond the hostName spec field.</li>
  <li>Platform upgrades: Added support for Kubernetes 1.31, NiFi 1.28, and NiFi 2.3.</li>
  <li>Bug fixes:</li>
  <li>NiFi Registry resources not cleaned up on delete, i.e. PVCs and Certificate Secrets.</li>
  <li>NiFi Registry hostname not added to Node Certificate.</li>
  <li>NiFi Registry users and authorizations incorrectly persisted.</li>
  <li>NiFi not restarting when additional CA bundles are provided.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="upgrading-to-the-new-release">Upgrading to the New Release</h2>
<p>Reference the latest operator version in the Helm Install command. More details can be found in the <a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/cfm-operator/2.9.0/installation/topics/cfm-op-install-cfm-op.html">installation instructions</a>.</p>

<h2 id="links">Links</h2>
<p><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/cfm-operator/2.9.0/release-notes/topics/cfm-op-whats-new.html">Release notes</a></p>

<p><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/cfm-operator/2.9.0/index.html">Documentation</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Matison</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="cloudera" /><category term="nifi" /><category term="kubernetes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Data In Motion Team is pleased to announce the release of Cloudera Flow Management - Kubernetes Operator version 2.10.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cloudera Data Flow 2.10 for Cloudera on Cloud</title><link href="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-DataFlow-2.10/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloudera Data Flow 2.10 for Cloudera on Cloud" /><published>2025-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera%20DataFlow%202.10</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cldr-steven-matison.github.io//blog/Cloudera-DataFlow-2.10/"><![CDATA[<p>The Data In Motion Team is pleased to announce the release of Cloudera Data Flow 2.10 for Cloudera on Cloud.</p>

<p>This release introduces NiFi 2 as generally available in Data Flow. Along with seamless NiFi 2 migrations, this  positions Data Flow as the ideal platform to migrate, build, and deploy NiFi 2 flows with minimal operational effort. In addition, it includes features that improve developer productivity, operational costs and security.</p>

<h2 id="release-highlights">Release Highlights</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Build and deploy on NiFi 2: Users can now develop flows in the Flow Designer as NiFi 2.3 flows by default. NiFi 2.3 will also be available as the NiFi 2 runtime for Flow Deployments. This marks the general availability of NiFi 2 in Data Flow.</li>
  <li>Time and cost savings on NiFi 2 migrations: Self-service migration is powered by Data Flow Catalog and Flow Designer. Users can organize NiFi 1 flows in Catalog, start migrations with one click, and make any required changes in Flow Designer. A comprehensive visual migration report clearly highlights items that require manual updates, while enabling users to effectively keep track of their progress.</li>
  <li>Improved developer productivity: Users can accelerate deployment processes by importing and referencing Shared Parameter Groups during deployment. This streamlined workflow significantly reduces development and deployment complexity and accelerates time to value for users by eliminating manual copy&amp;paste of parameter values.</li>
  <li>Improved cost efficiency: Users can now specify tailored storage capacity, IOPS, and throughput sizes  for their NiFi repositories, making smaller deployments more cost-efficient.</li>
  <li>Strengthened security: Collections enhance security by enabling precise role based access control for cataloged flows. Users can organize cataloged flows into Collections and tightly manage user access to each Collection.</li>
  <li>Secured inbound connections: Users can specify trusted IP addresses for flows with inbound connections, which will limit traffic to only the specified IP addresses.</li>
  <li>Better notifications: Users can now stay better informed with enhanced, customizable notifications:
    <ul>
      <li>Subscribe to deployment-specific alerts and customize notifications by event severity.</li>
      <li>Set up KPI-level subscriptions and notifications, including a URL that directs you to the affected NiFi component on the NiFi Canvas.</li>
      <li>Create distribution lists to ensure team-wide notification delivery.</li>
      <li>Integrate notifications directly with Slack (Technical Preview).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Platform upgrades: Added support for Kubernetes 1.31 and NiFi 1.28.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="upgrading-to-the-new-release">Upgrading to the New Release</h2>
<p>Customers can perform an in-place upgrade from supported Cloudera Data Flow  versions to 2.10. Alternatively, disabling and re-enabling an existing Data Flow environment will result in the re-enabled environment running the latest version.</p>

<h2 id="links">Links</h2>
<p><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/dataflow/cloud/release-notes/topics/cdf-whats-new.html">Release notes</a></p>

<p><a href="https://docs.cloudera.com/dataflow/cloud/index.html">Documentation</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Matison</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Cloudera Data Flow" /><category term="nifi" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Data In Motion Team is pleased to announce the release of Cloudera Data Flow 2.10 for Cloudera on Cloud.]]></summary></entry></feed>